Guide to the Ralph Bates Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ralph Bates Papers
1930-2002
1960-1995
GEN MSS 1013
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.64
(14 boxes)
The Papers contain correspondence with literary colleagues and family, most 1960s-1990s; drafts and reviews of novels and short stories, 1960s-2000; writings of others about Bates, most 1980s-1990s; audiocassettes of lectures by Bates about literature, 1960s-1970s, and interviews with him about his life and writings, 1980s; personal papers, including biographical information and legal documents, 1930s-1970s; a few photographs and documents concerning his International Brigade service during the Spanish Civil War; and materials relating to Jonathan Bates's imprisonment in Syria, 1972-1974, including correspondence with American and Syrian officials, legal documents, notes, and clippings.
Bates, Ralph, 1899-2000
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the George Henry Nettleton Fund, 2003.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 13-14 (audiocassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Ralph Bates (1899-2000)
English author; wrote novels about Spain; served with Republican forces in the Spanish Civil War; professor of creative writing and English literature at New York University, 1947-1966; later lived in Naxos, Greece. Bates was married to Eve Salzman; their son Jonathan Bates was imprisoned in Syria on charges of espionage, 1972-1974.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Correspondence, 1960s-1990s. II. Writings, 1964-2000. III. Writings of Others, 1943-1996. IV. Personal Papers, 1930-2002. V. Papers Relating to Jonathan Bates's Imprisonment in Syria, 1972-1974.
Scope and Contents
The Papers contain correspondence with literary colleagues and family, most 1960s-1990s; drafts and reviews of novels and short stories, 1960s-2000; writings of others about Bates, most 1980s-1990s; audiocassettes of lectures by Bates about literature, 1960s-1970s, and interviews with him about his life and writings, 1980s; personal papers, including biographical information and legal documents, 1930s-1970s; a few photographs and documents concerning his International Brigade service during the Spanish Civil War; and materials relating to Jonathan Bates's imprisonment in Syria, 1972-1974, including correspondence with American and Syrian officials, legal documents, notes, and clippings.
Authors, English -- 20th Century -- Archives; Prisoners -- Syria; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Literature and the war; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, British; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives, British; Syria -- Foreign relations -- United States; United States -- Foreign relations -- Syria; Audiocassettes -- United States -- 20th Century; Audiovisual materials -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographs -- 20th Century; Authors -- England -- 20th Century; Bates, Ralph, 1899-2000; Bates, Jonathan, 1942-; Behrend, Hanna, 1933-; Hart-Davis, Rupert, 1907-1999; Klaus, H. Gustav, 1944-; Ross, Alan, 1922-2001; Salzman, Eve; West, Rebecca, 1892-1983
- Correspondence, 1960s-1990s; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent name, followed by unsorted correspondence.
  Scope and Contents
  Contains incoming correspondence, with some outgoing drafts and carbons, and some third-party correspondence of Eve Salzman. Some letters are accompanied by writings of others.
  Related Materials
  See also additional correspondence in the Writing series and the Papers Relating to Jonathan Bates's Imprisonment in Syria series.
  - Bates, Jonathan, 1977-1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Behrend, Hanna, 1984-1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Chatto & Windus, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Hart-Davis, Rupert, 1982, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Klaus, H. Gustav, 1979-1988 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes letter from Bates to Klaus about Stephen Spender
  - Manetti, Daniela, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miró, Micheline, 1988-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Oxford University Press, 1998 June 23 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rollyson, Carl E. (Carl Edmund), 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Ross, Alan, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - West, Rebecca, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Unsorted, 1960s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
- Writings, 1964-2000, undated; 3.13; (7.5 boxes)
  Writings listed by title include drafts and reviews of novels; drafts and printed clippings of short stories and poems; and an audio recording of a short story draft. Some unpublished writings are listed under working titles. Other writings include unidentified short stories and unsorted review of novels.
  Arranged alphabetically by title, followed by lectures, arranged chronologically; other writings, arranged by genre; and unsorted writings.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 13 and 14 contain audiovisual material (audiocassettes). Restricted fragile. Reference copies are available upon request. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "Aquarius." Typescript photocopy (Box 2, Folder 16-20)
    "Working title"
  - "Beer Song." Autograph manuscript (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - "The Burning Corn" (short story). Printed, with revisions (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - "Conquistidor" (novel). Autograph manuscript (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
  - "Conversations in Mexico" (article). Printed (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Death of a Virgin" (novella). Printed (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - The Dolphin in the Wood (novel). Clippings of reviews (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "Elly Constantinos." Autograph manuscript (Box 3, Folder 29)
    Also titled: "Eleni Konstantinos"
  - The Fields of Paradise (novel). Notes and drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript (Box 3, Folder 30-34)
  - The Fields of Paradise (novel). Clippings of reviews (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - "Flight into Egypt" (short story). Drafts, computer printout (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - "The Heart Pierced Through" (short story). Printed (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - "The Haunted Man" (novella). Autograph manuscript and typescript, revised (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - "In Shining Naxos" (memoir). Drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, revised (Box 4, Folder 39-42)
  - "In Shining Naxos" (memoir). Drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, revised (Box 5, Folder 43-46)
  - "The Journey to Mount Diadem" (novel). Drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, revised (Box 5, Folder 47-48)
  - "Journey to the Sandalwood Forest" (novel). Typescript carbon, revised (Box 6, Folder 49-50)
  - Lean Men (novel). Clippings of reviews (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - "The Little She-Elephant" (short story). Printed (Box 6, Folder 52-53)
  - "Manhattan Underground" (novella). Drafts, typescript, revised (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Bates' "Maria", 1st version, 2000; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369382)
    The audiocassette's case reads, "His last attempt to write, or create a story, dictated to Jonathan Bates, early in 2000.
  - "Maria's Story" (short story). Computer printout, revised (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - The Olive Field (novel). Printed excerpts, photocopy (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - The Olive Field (novel). Clippings of reviews (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - "Peter Cavallini." Typescript, revised (Box 6, Folder 59-62)
  - Rainbow Fish (novel). Clippings of reviews (Box 7, Folder 63)
  - Sirocco and Other Stories (short story collection). Book jackets, photocopy (Box 7, Folder 64)
  - Sirocco and Other Stories (short story collection). Clippings of reviews (Box 7, Folder 65-66)
  - The Undiscoverables and Other Stories (short story collection). Clippings of reviews (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - "The Winged Mountain" (collection of poems). Computer printout (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - Lectures
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies are available upon request. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Audio-Forum. "The House of Atreus & the Great Chain of Evil" (1 of 2 audiocassettes), 1968; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369390)
      Given at the University of California, Santa Cruz
    - Audio-Forum. "The House of Atreus & the Great Chain of Evil" (2 of 2 audiocassettes), 1968; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369408)
    - Audio-Forum Sound Seminars. "Odysseus: The Eternal Optimist and Searcher for Truth", 1970; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369416)
    - "A Weekend in Hell" I, New York University, Tarrytown (1 of 4 audiocassettes), 1967 April 15-16; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369424)
      Seminar on hell as a subject in the arts.
    - "A Weekend in Hell" II, 1, New York University, Tarrytown (2 of 4 audiocassettes), 1967 April 15-16; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369432)
    - "A Weekend in Hell" II, 2, New York University, Tarrytown (3 of 4 audiocassettes), 1967 April 15-16; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369457)
    - "A Weekend in Hell" III, New York University, Tarrytown (4 of 4 audiocassettes), 1967 April 15-16; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369440)
    - "Greek Tragedy: Origins and Development". Lecture Series. Poetry Center of the 92nd Street Y, New York City (1 of 4 audiocassettes), 1964; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369465)
    - "Aeschylus". Lecture Series. Poetry Center of the 92nd Street Y, New York City (2 of 4 audiocassettes), undated; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369473)
    - "Sophocles". Lecture Series. Poetry Center of the 92nd Street Y, New York City (3 of 4 audiocassettes), undated; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369481)
    - "Euripides". Lecture Series. Poetry Center of the 92nd Street Y, New York City (4 of 4 audiocassettes), undated; 1 (Box 13, Item barcode 39002099369499)
    - "The Epic in Literature". Lecture Series. Poetry Center of the 92nd Street Y, New York City (1 of 4 audiocassettes), 1964; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369507)
    - "Paradise Lost" and "The Aeneid". Lecture Series. Poetry Center of the 92nd Street Y, New York City (2 of 4 audiocassettes), 1964; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369515)
    - "The Aeneid". Lecture Series. Poetry Center of the 92nd Street Y, New York City (3 of 4 audiocassettes), 1964; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369523)
    - "The Odyssey: A Modern Sequel". Lecture Series. Poetry Center of the 92nd Street Y, New York City (4 of 4 audiocassettes), 1964; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369531)
  - Other Writings
    - Lists of writings (Box 7, Folder 84-85)
    - Short stories (Box 7, Folder 86)
    - Short stories. German translatations by Hanna Behrend (Box 7, Folder 87-88)
    - Unsorted (Box 8, Folder 89-92)
    - Unsorted reviews (Box 8, Folder 93)
- Writings of Others, 1943-1996, undated; 1.04; (2.5 boxes)
  - Manetti, Daniela. Academic thesis on writings of Ralph Bates. Printed, 1980s (Box 8, Folder 94)
  - Miró, Micheline. Le mexique et la litterature anglaise de Lawrence a Lowry. Dissertation, printed, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 95-96)
  - Miró, Micheline. Le mexique et la litterature anglaise de Lawrence a Lowry. Dissertation, printed, 1988 (Box 10, Folder 97)
  - Miró, Micheline. "Nouvelles d'Espagne par Ralph Bates." Computer printout, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 98-99)
  - Articles about Ralph Bates. Clippings and photocopies, 1978-1991, undated (Box 10, Folder 100-102)
  - Unsorted, 1943-1995, undated (Box 10, Folder 103-104)
- Personal Papers, 1930-2002, undated; 0.63; (1.5 boxes)
  Includes biographical information and obituaries; audiocassettes of interviews with Bates; identification documents; and an International Brigade discharge document and photographs relating to his service in the Spanish Civil War.
  Box 14 contains audiovisual material (audiocassettes). Restricted fragile. Reference copies are available upon request. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Audio-Forum, undated (Box 11, Folder 105)
  - Biographical audiotape recordings: conversations with Daniela Manetti, Fiesole, Italy, 1988-1989; 10 (Box 14)
    - One, 1988-1989; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369549)
    - Two, 1988-1989; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369556)
    - Three, 1988-1989; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369564)
    - Four, 1988-1989; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369572)
    - Five, 1988-1989; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369580)
    - Six, 1988-1989; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369598)
    - Seven, 1988-1989; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369606)
    - Eight, 1988-1989; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369614)
    - Nine, 1988-1989; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369622)
    - Ten, 1988-1989; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369630)
  - Ralph Bates: Recollections, Conversation with son Jonathan, 1989 December; 1 (Box 14, Item barcode 39002099369648)
  - Other biographical information, 1981-2002, undated (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - Identification documents, 1930-1973, undated (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Kunst und Macht (exhibition, Deutsches Historisches Museum), 1996 (Box 11, Folder 119-120)
    Includes photographs of Ralph Bates. Includes letters from Peter Hillebrand.
  - Obituaries, 2000-2001 (Box 11, Folder 121)
  - Spain, 1936-1938, undated (Box 11, Folder 122)
    Includes photographs of Ralph Bates in Spain, 1936-1938
- Papers Relating to Jonathan Bates's Imprisonment in Syria, 1972-1974, undated; 0.42; (1.5 boxes)
  Arranged roughly chronologically.
  Also see correspondence with Jonathan Bates in the Correspondence series.
  - Correspondence and other papers, 1972-1974, undated (Box 11, Folder 123-130)
  - Correspondence and other papers (Box 12, Folder 131-133)